It explodes like 12 sticks of dynamite!
12 Angry Men is a drama film directed by Sidney Lumet.
The defense and the prosecution have rested and the jury is filing into the jury room to
decide if a young Spanish-American is guilty or innocent of murdering his father.
What begins as an open and shut case soon becomes a mini-drama of each of the jurors'
prejudices and preconceptions about the trial, the accused, and each other.
Juror 1, played by Martin Balsam.
Juror 2, played by John Fiedler.
Juror 3, played by Lee J. Cobb.
Juror 4, played by E.G. Marshall.
Juror 5, played by Jack Klugman.
Juror 6, played by Edward Binns.
12 Angry Men is a 1957 American legal drama film directed by Sidney Lumet in his
feature directorial debut, adapted by Reginald Rose from his 1954 teleplay.
A critique of the American jury system during the McCarthy era, the film tells the story of a jury of twelve men as they deliberate the conviction or acquittal of a
teenager charged with murder on the basis of reasonable doubt; disagreement and conflict among the jurors forces them to question their morals and values.
It stars an ensemble cast, featuring Henry Fonda (who
also produced the film with Rose), Lee J.
Cobb, Ed Begley, E.
Marshall, and Jack Warden.
An independent production distributed by United Artists, 12 Angry Men received
acclaim from critics, despite a lukewarm box-office performance.
At the 30th Academy Awards, it was nominated for Best
Picture, Best Director and Best Screenplay.
It is regarded by many as one of the greatest films ever made.
In 2007, it was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically or aesthetically significant".
Additionally, it was selected as the second-best courtroom drama ever (after 1962's To Kill a
Mockingbird) by the American Film Institute for their AFI's 10 Top 10 list.
The film explores themes of death penalty, anonymity, court case, judge, jurors.
The tone is emotional.